Hello, everyone and welcome to English Pot.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today we're
talking about a very important topic.
This is about time.
That's right. So sometimes
we are a little bit lazy or
maybe we sleep too much and
we're late to work or a meeting.
Alright, so learn many different
ways to talk about being late today.
Let's take a listen to our dialogue.
Okay everyone, shall we begin?
Sorry Maggie, but we're missing a
few people. Can we hang on a sec?
Well, I did say 11 o'clock
sharp and it's now five past, so...
Hi everyone. I'm so sorry I'm late.
It's raining cats and dogs outside
and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
Okay James, take a seat quickly please.
Right, the subject of the
meeting is the importance.
Hi guys, please excuse me.
I was held up in traffic.
Right, as I was saying the
subject of the meeting is...
Hi Maggie, I'm terribly sorry.
The traffic is murder out there.
Sit down bro, no?
Okay now, as you're
aware, the topic of the
meeting is the importance
of being punctual.
Who would like to start?
Alright, we're back,
so now let's take a look
at some of this vocab
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So first up we have a word that we heard.
The phrase was, I did say 11 o'clock sharp.
Okay, so if you say the
time, like 11 o'clock and
then you add sharp at the
end, what does that mean?
That means exactly.
So, 11 o'clock, exactly 11 o'clock,
11 0 0, not 11 o'clock, not 11 o'clock.
So if I say I'll be there
at 3 o'clock sharp.
That means you won't be there at 2
58, so you will not be there at 3 o'clock.
Oh, 4, you'll be there at 3 o'clock.
That's right.
Okay, so 3 o'clock sharp.
So if you say the time and then you
add sharp, it means at that exact time.
Now, James was late, he said he was late
because he had to wait ages for a taxi.
Okay, so this might be
confusing for some people,
Marco, because I can
say, what's your age?
How old are you?
But here ages has a different meaning.
So I have to wait ages means
I waited a very long time.
That's right.
So the word ages means
for a very long time.
It's always related to time and innocence.
Exactly.
So I could say, Marco,
it's so good to see you.
I haven't seen you in ages.
That means I haven't seen
you in such a long time.
Okay, very good.
And now the next person Sally came
in and she said she was held up in traffic.
Okay, to be held up in traffic
means to be stuck in traffic.
That means you were made late because
there were so many cars on the road.
Okay, so somebody or
something else made you late.
That's right.
So to be held up means to be made late.
I could ask you, Marco,
why are you so late?
What held you up?
Exactly. What held you up?
That means what made me late.
That's right.
I could give you many different things.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it could be traffic or maybe I
could be held up by the doctor.
Maybe he took longer than what I expected.
Or there's no elevator
and I'm waiting for the
elevator and I got
held up by the elevator.
Okay.
Very good.
And now the importance of being punctual.
That's the topic of the meeting.
And so what is this word punctual?
Okay.
So punctual is an adjective and it
describes something as being on time.
Okay.
So the opposite of this word would be what?
So the opposite would be late.
Late.
Okay.
So she's a very punctual student.
She always comes to class on time.
She's never late punctual.
So you describe a person
as being punctual or not.
That's right.
Okay.
Very good.
We view all this vocab.
Let's go back and listen
to the dialogue again.
Okay.
Everyone, shall we begin?
Sorry, Maggie.
But we're missing a few people.
Can we hang on a sec?
Well, I did say 11 o'clock
sharp and it's now five past.
So.
Hi, everyone.
I'm so sorry.
I'm late.
It's raining cats and dogs outside
and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
Okay, James.
Take a seat quickly, please.
Right.
The subject of the
meeting is the importance.
Hi, guys.
Please excuse me.
I was held up in traffic.
Right.
As I was saying the
subject of the meeting is.
Hi, Maggie.
I'm terribly sorry.
The traffic is murder out there.
Sit down, bro.
No.
Okay.
Now, as you're aware, the topic for the
meeting is the importance of being punctual.
Who would like to start?
All right, now let's take a look at
some phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
We have a lot of really great
phrases today that describe.
Well, that are excuses for not being
on time or for not being punctual.
The first one we heard was
actually different though.
One of the students said,
can we hang on a sec?
Hang on a sec.
Okay.
So if you ask someone to
hang on, that means to wait.
Hang on.
Wait.
Yeah, exactly.
So hang on just means to wait.
It's very casual.
Okay.
Now, if we add a sec,
hang on a sec or hang on
a minute, that means
wait for a little while.
A little while.
A sec.
S-E-C stands for second.
And it's very common in this phrase.
We hear hang on a sec or wait a sec.
Wait a sec.
Okay.
Very good.
So it's very casual.
It's very spoken English.
Although the word sec doesn't really exist.
It's just a short way of saying second.
Mm-hmm.
Exactly.
And later on, we heard James come in.
He was one of those people
that we had to wait for.
And he said, it's raining
cats and dogs outside.
That's right.
Okay.
It's raining cats and dogs.
So our cats and dogs falling from the sky.
They are not.
So this might sound very weird to you.
This does not mean there are cats
and dogs falling down from the clouds.
But it does mean that it's raining a lot.
It's raining really hard outside.
Okay.
Very good.
So it's a phrase used
to say it's raining a lot.
It's raining very, very hard.
Mm-hmm.
Raining cats and dogs.
So Maggie is trying to
continue with the meeting
as many people keep
coming in and disrupting her.
So she says, right.
As I was saying, the
subject of the meeting.
As I was saying, now this
is a really important phrase
because you're going to
hear this a lot in meeting.
In meetings or in conversations
where someone is distracted.
Mm-hmm.
So, okay.
We're having, oh, wait.
I'm sorry.
I have to talk to this person over here.
When you want to come
back to what you were
talking about, you want
to return to the topic.
You say, as I was saying.
That's right.
Mm-hmm.
As I was saying.
So maybe you were interrupted.
Maybe you got distracted.
And you want to continue talking
about the same topic as I was saying.
And then you continue talking.
So you return to the
original point you are making.
Okay.
Very good.
And, well, Bruno was
the last guy to come in
and he said that traffic
is murder out there.
Okay.
So murder, to murder means to kill someone.
Mm-hmm.
But we're not talking
about killing people here.
We're talking about an analogy.
We're saying it says bad as murder.
Wow.
So in this case, traffic is murder
means traffic is really awful.
It's really terrible outside.
So in what other situation
or with what other noun
instead of traffic can we
use this, something is murder?
The weight is murder.
Okay.
So that means you have to
wait a very, very long time.
Uh-huh.
Okay.
All right.
Very good.
So now why don't we
go back to the dialogue.
Let's have one last review
and we'll be right back.
Okay, everyone.
Shall we begin?
Very Maggie, but we're
missing a few people.
Can we hang on a sec?
Well, I did say 11 o'clock
sharp and it's now five past.
So... Hi, everyone.
I'm so sorry I'm late.
It's raining cats and dogs outside
and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
Okay, James.
Take a seat quickly, please.
Right.
The subject of the
meeting is the importance.
Hi, guys.
Please excuse me.
I was held up in traffic.
Right.
As I was saying the subject
of the meeting is... Hi, Maggie.
I'm terribly sorry.
The traffic is murder out there.
Sit down, bro.
No.
Okay, now.
As you're aware, the topic for the meeting
is the importance of being punctual.
Who would like to start?
So Marco, are you a punctual
person or are you usually late?
Not for social gatherings,
I'm usually pretty punctual.
For work, I'm usually very late.
I noticed you're one of the last
people to come in in the morning.
Yeah.
Usually for work I arrive
late, but not like too late.
You know, some people may even
be an hour or two or something.
A couple of minutes,
15 minutes is all right.
So I do hate to wait if we agree to meet
up at 2 o'clock and you come in at 2 30,
I don't know, let's say to the movies,
then I think that's really irritating.
I agree.
That's... I'm a very punctual
person and I get very
annoyed when people are
late to meetings or when
people come late to
appointments, some of our parties.
Yeah, and I think it's
different in different
countries because, you
know, in many different
places, they have what
they call the local time.
So if you say, okay,
the meetings at 9, then
everyone assumes that
the meeting is supposed
to start at 9, but then
everyone comes in at
9, but grabs a cup
of coffee, talks at the
cooler, gets their
seat, checks their email,
and then the meeting will
start at 9 30 instead of 9.
Or, for example, the
transportation you will
find in different countries can
be punctual or not punctual.
Right.
In Germany, their
transportation is very famous
for being punctual,
but in India, you will
find that the trains
are not very punctual.
You might wait one or
two or six hours for a train.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So it's different in different countries.
I imagine that in a place
like Germany would be
very, it would be
considered a very bad thing
to arrive late to a
meeting, for example.
Yeah, I'm curious about that.
So let us know, is
it acceptable in your
country to be a little bit late to
a meeting or to an appointment?
Is punctuality important?
Let us know.
Our website is www.engospot.com.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
Bye.